[SPEAKER_00]: So, a few more questions that are kind of suitable for reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: I came up and I thought maybe we can just, like, address and go through, like, practical, like, how to practically think about and reflect on certain topics that can really be the the basis for the right type of meditation, instead of, you know, the the common self-hypnotic
[SPEAKER_00]: Attitudes and outcomes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think one of the most fundamental things, really, that everybody should be clear about with themselves, it's... Why do I meditate?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what is the purpose?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is the outcome I'm hoping for to...
[SPEAKER_00]: As a result of my meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whatever that meditation is, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: We don't have to get into that now here.
[SPEAKER_00]: The rights and wrongs.
[SPEAKER_00]: We have plenty of talks that deal with those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's more like just whatever notion of meditation that you have, like what is the reason behind it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is that something you're clear about?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that something that you clearly see, kind of, the path outlined, required, the outcomes of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And where are those motivations rooted in?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do you hope to achieve?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I think very often
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, people read the suttas, get the sense of contemporary Buddhism, various teachers, instructions, find meditation techniques and so on, and it's helpful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it does kind of always go hand in hand with these Buddhist instructions that are found in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, they talk about freedom and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Freedom from suffering, freedom from desire, freedom from hindrances, but I think more often than not, if you think about it today, like on today's terms, just that notion of freedom, it's quite ambiguous, because people haven't really, you know, sat and philosophically really get to the bottom of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it mean to be free, for example?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, you know, feels like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have some notions, but more often than not, it's simply misrepresented, misconceived and confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, practically speaking, if you were to take a sample of your, like, average, average meditators and so on, I think more people would be confusing just a notion of, eh... peace, whatever, whatever has, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever has kind of enabled me to get some sense of peace, they would confuse that for freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would think, oh, that's the freedom that the Buddha was talking about in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... so that's... therefore, when I sit and meditate free from distractions, free from things that disturb me in a... in a controlled environment, I am peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that... that equals freedom, or that's bringing me closer to freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, as I said before so many times, if you actually look at the suttas correctly, as a whole body of instruction, as the broadest context of instruction that the Buddha gave to people, yeah, the peace is kind of the result of freedom, not other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might have peaceful experiences here and there, but if you're confusing peace with freedom, means you would be
[SPEAKER_00]: More often than not, confusing a mere agreeable circumstances, comfort, with things up to your liking or within your control, you will confuse that for a path of freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that that couldn't be further from the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's kind of what happens, basically, when such confusion exists, when such misrepresentation exists in people, they would be merely pretty much going around hunting refined pleasures, refined peacefulness, and at the pretext of freedom, freedom from suffering, and so on, and other things that let's talk about, but in reality, just kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Creating this this mask of an underlying agitation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by equating the peaceful state, we could put it that way, I guess, by equating the peaceful state, you kind of end up still acting out of the the same cravings that were
[SPEAKER_00]: Disturbing your peace, like in any other scenario.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, your pursuit of the peaceful states become like a subtle indulgence in a... very much in like a... in a central domain, in the form of central craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like a coarsely going after the desires, but the same motivation that you have when you desire sense objects or when you desire to act out of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, the same desire to be peaceful
[SPEAKER_00]: That's confused for freedom or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's basically... that desire is still the central desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if you invest like years and years of effort in like building this this elaborate environment and system that supports the practice of peace, that supports the non-disturbance, that supports pretty much all the circumstances that might be involved in it,
[SPEAKER_00]: If that original motivation and that desire is never questioned towards peaceful states as valuable, it's never questioned, never reflected upon, it's... the whole thing will still be a projection within the central domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be still rooted in central craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why, more often than not, people today would train rightly if they were enduring the friction of the present moment, of the things that are kind of pressuring you, disturbing you, then just going blindly or at face value following peaceful states.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if you do get peaceful states, you put them in a bracket, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: You step back and you don't lose perspective in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's like all of this, as I often keep saying, can be realigned correctly and rekindled through right questioning.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you find meditation helpful, you find sitting peacefully helpful, that's fine, but you gotta not take that for granted and also try and understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: But not...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't even understand peace, why peace is peaceful, but I understand why is it that what you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why do you think the practice is about being peaceful, for example?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, it's not like a...
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to find the right answer, the wrong answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more like I need to find the answer that pertains to my motivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, why do I want this?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what do I think freedom is?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do I think meditation is?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do I think practice is?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when I dutifully keep the precepts and sit and meditate or go on retreat and stuff, what exactly am I hoping to achieve?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I see that path of achievement clearly outlined, as in like, oh, if I do this, I clearly understand the results of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it all based on kind of a vague notion of, well, something good will happen out of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something good will come out of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in the meantime, I prefer it because I feel peaceful and comfortable.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think more often than not, that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, if people confuse the peace for freedom, as in any peace they can get by any means necessary for freedom, they will inevitably
[SPEAKER_00]: I fall into a trap of pretty much needing and preferring comfort and confusing that for the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when I live in the environment, when there are no disturbances,
[SPEAKER_00]: When there are no physical endeavors, because usually like most of the... even like most of the monasteries and stuff become that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many of the places become like very kind of precious and padded around the environment, so people become more and more and more and more sheltered, and that practically results just living in a constant... in a comfort that you couldn't have pretty much afforded even as a layperson.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like comfort... when I say comfort, I don't mean like...
[SPEAKER_00]: Luxurious beds and stuff like that, sure, that can easily be done with, but it's more like... it's quite a privilege to be able to live in the environment where there are no sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches bombarding you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... but do you take that within the right context or do you take that for granted and just start to depend now on the environment when there are no provocations?
[SPEAKER_00]: The environment that's comfortable, because you don't have to deal with anything, because nothing comes up, because there's nothing disturbing you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not a problem to seek a suitable, peaceful environment, but if you're doing it for the wrong reasons, it will lead to nowhere anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is, like, like, are you afraid, for example, are you afraid of being disturbed by the external circumstances?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, would that undermine your meditation?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would that threaten it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, that's not the meditation you should be cultivating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, the whole samādhi, the principle behind, the suttas often talk about, it's like immovability, imperturbability, in face of sights that want to move you, smells that want to move you, touches and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yes, physical withdrawal necessary in order to support the precepts,
[SPEAKER_00]: But, the work still needs to be done towards the actual freedom of imperturbability, and not fall into a trap of, oh, I've withdrawn myself from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I live in a controlled environment where there are, most of the time, there are no distractions, no bombardments of sensuality, no disturbances, no physical work, no labor, not really having to endure sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, heat, cold, all those things that suttas talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then people would kind of fall into that sort of trap of
[SPEAKER_00]: being completely dependent on that very artificial environment and taking for granted and even confusing it for peace, because there's nothing disturbing me here, therefore I'm not disturbed, therefore for me there is no work to do, even if obviously internally people know that there is plenty of work to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why it's like
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to start questioning your motivation way before you become that dependent on these artificial circumstances, that... because, again, you're depending on comfort, you're depending on sense of control, and that's not going to be easy to undo.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you sit and meditate, or you sit and contemplate, another thing you could be asking yourself, am I truly, actually, seeking liberation that the Buddha was talking about?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, is that what I am aiming at?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, am I just, deep down, really just want a slightly better way to hide from suffering when it comes?
[SPEAKER_00]: A slightly stronger lid to keep on top of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: A slightly better way to manage?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, what do I want, basically?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's pretty much what you should be asking yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when I'm doing this practice, when I'm practicing the dhamma, when I'm studying the suttas, when I'm meditating, when I'm contemplating, what do I want from it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is my goal?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, how far do I want to go?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I even... have I thought about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as I said, if these motivations are never revealed, they will be aligned with, pretty much, the place where you come from.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the place you come from, it's always going to be in the beginning the place of desire, the place of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the more you do your practices of the dhamma, whatever you think those are, without
[SPEAKER_00]: Unraveling and revealing these, as I said, the context of your motivation as to why you're doing in the first place, what's your tacit kind of assumptions and implications, then everything you do in the in the name of practice, your meditation, the precepts, everything, it's just going to become basically a
[SPEAKER_00]: An extension, like a subtle continuation of the subtle addiction to the sense of control, to comfort, to the preferences, to avoiding pain, prolonging pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it just becomes very much the extension of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't really uproot anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why, again, through the questioning, you would reveal this motivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, when
[SPEAKER_00]: Your intentions behind why you're meditating, why you're doing this, become somewhat clearer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, new questions will arise, or new questions will present themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, am I seeking peace with a view that such peace and freedom will come on account of full understanding, say, of suffering, of feelings, of craving, fully training my mind out of the desire?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do I deep down still carry an assumption that that peace will just sort of be bestowed upon me, if I do these random things rightly, long enough, I will have a breakthrough, which is kind of a form of like an instant gratification of what you've been working for, like a reward.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm doing this, I'm doing this, I don't see the connection, I don't see the clear... like there's no clear understanding, as I said, of the outcomes and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I'm just doing it because it makes some sense, I learned about it, and I'm waiting for the peace, for liberation, for whatever you want to call it, to happen to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the difference between, like, are you actually developing it as something that you understood how to be developed, or you're just doing random stuff and then hoping that development was just going to come your way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's like... and, yeah, say, if you ask these questions as a part of your meditation and contemplation, you might get different answers at different times.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, sometimes your motivation might be leaning one way, sometimes might be the other way, sometimes old views might creep in.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, again, maintaining the clarity of that context
[SPEAKER_00]: And broadening it, in that sense, with a further clarification, is something that you can't have too much of.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Sutta said, like you can't have too much of sati, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, see, all of these other subtle and tacit little views that you might have here and there, are going to start floating up to the surface.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like another sea.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start questioning yourself, why am I meditating?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I really, you know, seeking freedom from suffering the way the suttas outline it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, you know, I just want to feel basically peaceful and undisturbed here and now, but I'm not really willing to give up too many things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That already shows you, like, what direction your mind is leaning, what direction the animal is preferring.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you can already contrast that with the instruction that the Buddha gave and say, well, is that aligned with what the Buddha said?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that aligned with, you know, countless of statements of saying sensuality is an obstruction?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensual desires are peril, they're in the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Acting out of will-will is unwholesome, it's ignoble and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you could already then see whether you are trying to practice dhamma on your own terms or you are actually trying to align it with how it's presented in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because then that kind of leads to natural questions like, okay, so, how about if I practice the dhamma or say, how about I'm seeking?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's fine to want to be peaceful and it's fine to want to be happy.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no problem with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just how you go about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you just acting to... are you just sort of investing your efforts that are still very much driven and rooted by the same central desire that you are completely refusing to question?
[SPEAKER_00]: Emotional preferences?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or are you willing to go against those if needed?
[SPEAKER_00]: So then the question you should be asking... you could be asking yourself if you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you don't have to do any of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you want, it's like, could I
[SPEAKER_00]: Even imagine, say, being happy, being content, being peaceful even, yeah, without needing to do anything on account of anything that happens to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is that a possibility for me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, is that a possibility for my mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's not, can I imagine it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I imagine the benefits of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would that be a beneficial skill to develop?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, genuinely, it doesn't matter what comes your way, doesn't matter what happens to you, doesn't matter who says what, what you experience, whether you lose or you gain or whatever worldly wind blows blows your way, could you remain peaceful without needing to deal with anything that comes your way, without needing to move, without needing to do anything, without needing to act out, without needing to manage, without needing to counter,
[SPEAKER_00]: Could you remain untouched, pretty much?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you imagine how that would feel?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would that be a valuable thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, would it be a valuable thing to develop?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you can ask yourself, okay, so... How would one go about developing that?
[SPEAKER_00]: How would I do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if somebody were to ask you,
[SPEAKER_00]: Hey, how would you develop that?
[SPEAKER_00]: What comes to your mind as an answer?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, how is it that you understand?
[SPEAKER_00]: The imperturbability, immovability, contentment, peace, being above the suffering, like the lotus is above the water and the mud that it grew out of, and stuff like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the stuff they talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, can you wrap your head around it without, like, as I said, just resorting to, like, an answer, a line from the suttas or something?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, no, you're doing this as a contemplation, as a reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you sit quietly,
[SPEAKER_00]: As a part of your meditation, you actually want to be uncovering and revealing these very, sort of, views that you carry, inclinations, leanings, preferences, because that is how sati is developed, that's how sati is broadened, that's how sati becomes... the context becomes more established.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, so, like, can I be
[SPEAKER_00]: Untouched.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I be... or, say, even if I can't be untouched, I can't imagine how it would feel to be untouched by unpleasant things and so on, can I remain immovable?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, see, you might not have a choice whether you're touched or not, but you certainly have a choice whether you're going to act out of it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, do you see, do you recognize, can you discern the threshold, the extent of
[SPEAKER_00]: How far you could go, how far you could take on without needing to, you know, act out of panic or pressure or hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, where is that line?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it as soon as something unpleasant touches you, your mind spirals out of control and you're just acting out of all of these habits, firing on all cylinders just to cover it up, just to manage, just to regain the sense of pleasure and control and comfort and get rid of the pain?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or are you able to stay with it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, are you able to stay with the discomfort?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you able to stay with, like, mental threats that your own mind can be showing you, throwing at you?
[SPEAKER_00]: And where is the light?
[SPEAKER_00]: How far you can stay with it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, it's like these things need to be, like, you need to shine the light onto them through these reflections and questions, because otherwise they will remain, like, hidden
[SPEAKER_00]: As a guiding principle behind your efforts, investments and everything else, because you're not looking at them, they're there in the background influencing through preferences, through leanings, through these subtle cravings.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you don't
[SPEAKER_00]: Uncover the subtle cravings through, like, psychologizing about mechanics of cravings and results and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: You uncover them by questioning your own motivation, because craving is always where your desire is, where your intention is, to do this, to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by questioning that, unravelling, clearing out anything that's sort of covering it up, it's, you know, it can eventually reach a point where things are
[SPEAKER_00]: Clearly understood, on the level that they are, so that when you are touched by pleasure, touched by pain, there is enough of width, so to speak, in your mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: That you wouldn't fall into the trap of immediate reaction, immediate movement, immediate activation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, see, like, say something touches you, unpleasantly, and then you immediately have the habitual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say somebody said something upsetting, and you immediately have the habitual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: There will be just... and then, obviously, you'll be speaking, saying stuff, doing stuff, acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say that's somebody who's not restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you have been practicing, training rightly, restraining, reflecting, as I said, and delving deeper and deeper, or broader and broader, into these contexts and preconceived notions, you will find yourself in a position of something says... somebody says something upsetting to you, the upset is felt, and even the thoughts might start rushing out, but you remain still.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, oh,
[SPEAKER_00]: Look, all these floods came up, but I was not taken by them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, obviously, it's going to give you more confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, so can I develop this principle even further, whereby there'll be no even floods coming?
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason the floods were coming is because I was still liable to be kind of taken by them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, when I've sufficiently remained and practiced immovability on the level of body, speech, and mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: The floods dry up, basically, because I'm not there anymore, basically, to be taken by those same torrents and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, that can be a meditation, certainly for some period of time, because, as I said, plenty more questions
[SPEAKER_00]: It will come up if you start asking these things rightly and not immediately jumping in for an answer, as I said, but asking them and then staying in that mode of a question asked without defaulting to an answer that's going to satisfy and plug the hole, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ask a question and leave it there for a while.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't ignore it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't start thinking about something else and see what the question points at.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you start getting the answers that are more and more aligned with how things actually are, with the principles of the five aggregates and everything else that the Buddha talked about.